Finding Aid for Emerson Frank Greenman Papers, 1888-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Emerson Frank Greenman Papers 1888-1984, 1924-1972
Greenman, Emerson Frank, 1895-1973.
(in 8 boxes)
7 linear feet
851362 Aa 2
Emerson Frank Greenman was a prominent Michigan archaeologist who served as Curator of the Great Lakes Division of the Museum of Anthropology at the University of Michigan from 1945 to 1965. The Greenman papers include correspondence, administrative materials related to the Camp Killarney field school in Ontario, Canada, site files for archaeological sites in Canada, research and topical files, scrapbooks and photographs.
Sponsor: This finding aid is a product of a project supported by a grant awarded to the Bentley Historical Library and University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology in 2002 by the Division of Preservation and Access of the National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal agency.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the papers were transferred by the University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology (donor. no. 9273 ) in 2003. Photographs and one folder of correspondence were received from Greenman (donor. no. 1731 ) in several accessions in the 1960s.
Restricted access in part. Information on the location of archaeological sites is protected against disclosure under an Attorney General's opinion and is exempt from Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests. Site information is present in boxes 1-3 and 5-7 of the Greenman papers. For information on petitioning for access to site file information, please consult the reference archivist.
Emerson "Doc" Frank Greenman was born on September 10, 1895 in Hartwellville, Michigan. He originally entered the University of Michigan in 1916 as a student in the College of Engineering, but left when he was inducted into the U.S. Army in 1918. Greenman returned to Michigan in 1920, but this time as a student in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts. Studying under Wilbert Hinsdale, from whom he gained a particular appreciation for Michigan archaeology, and Alexander Ruthven, he received his A.B. in 1923.
From 1923 to 1924, Greenman attended Oxford University, receiving a diploma in anthropology. He also studied with the American School of Prehistoric Research in Europe in 1924. He then returned to the University of Michigan in the fall of 1924 to pursue doctoral studies in anthropology. He received his Ph.D. in 1927.
Though he was appointed as Curator of the Great Lakes Division of the Museum of Anthropology in 1927, Greenman choose to leave in April 1928 to take a position as the Curator of Archaeology at the Ohio State Archaeological and Historical Society. He remained there for seven years, during which time he directed excavations at a number of Woodland sites, including the Seip Mound, as well as at the Reeve, Tuttle Hill, and South Park Sites.
Greenman returned to the University of Michigan again in 1935 as a Research Associate in the Museum of Anthropology, a position he held for two years. Greenman was then promoted to Assistant Curator in 1937, Associate Curator in 1942, and Curator in 1945. Greenman held this position until his retirement in 1965. Greenman also taught in the Department of Anthropology, appointed as an Associate Professor in 1946 and promoted to Professor in 1965.
Greenman was an active field archaeologist, conducting excavations at many sites around the Great Lakes and publishing the results. His largest research program was the excavation of sites in the Manitoulin District of Ontario, Canada. Greenman led a field school in the area from 1938 to 1953. He also led major excavations at the Younge Site in 1935, and the Riviere aux Vase, Wolf and Furton Sites in 1936 and 1937. Greenman's major publications included The Younge Site: An Archaeological Record for Michigan (Museum of Anthropology Occasional Contribution no. 6, 1937), Guide to Serpent Mound (Ohio State Archaeological and Historical Society, 1939) and The Indians of Michigan (Michigan Historical Commission, 1961). Late in his career, Greenman became very interested in drawing connections between the Solutrean, an Upper Paleolithic culture of Europe, and the early cultures of the New World, publishing his hypotheses and findings in Current Anthropology in 1963.
Greenman did much to foster cooperation between professional and amateur archaeologists in Michigan. He was the first secretary-treasurer of the Michigan Archaeological Society (MAS), a position he held from 1950 until 1955 when he was named Honorary Secretary. He was also the first editor of Michigan Archaeologist, guiding the journal from 1953 through 1965. He was awarded the society's Distinguished Service plaque in 1963 and a festschrift issue of the Michigan Archaeologist was produced in his honor in 1965.
Greenman and his wife Edna were married in October 1927, and had three children, Mary, Emerson, and Sarah. Greenman died on June 24, 1973, in Ann Arbor.
The Emerson Frank Greenman Papers are comprised of six series: Correspondence, Camp Killarney, Research and Miscellaneous Files, Photographs, Scrapbooks, and Canadian Site Files.
Subjects:
Education--Michigan--Mount Pleasant.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; McBain (Mich.); Mount Pleasant (Mich.); Mount Pleasant Indian School.; Pontiac, Ottawa Chief, d. 1769.; Greenman, Emerson Frank, 1895-1973.; University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Michigan Archaeological Society.; Archaeology.; Excavations (Archaeology)--Ontario.; Manitoulin Island (Ont.); Ontario--Antiquities.; Indians of North America.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Michigan--Work.; Alcona County (Mich.); Au Train River (Mich.); Boats.; Cheboygan County (Mich.); Churches.; Clinton Inn (Clinton, Mich.); Clinton (Mich.)--Hotels and taverns.; Courthouses--Michigan--Monroe.; Cross Village (Mich.); Cutover lands.; Detroit (Mich.); Dwellings.; Fire engines and equipment.; Gogebic, Lake (Mich.); Hotels and taverns--Michigan--Clinton.; Huron County (Mich.); Huron, Lake (Mich. and Ont.); Indians of North America.; Ingham County (Mich.); Iosco County (Mich.); Log cabins.; Looking Glass River (Mich.); Lumber industry--1888.; Mackinac Island (Mich.); Michigan, Northern.; Military parades and ceremonies.; Mills--Michigan--Presque Ile County.; Missaukee County (Mich.); Monroe (Mich.)--Courthouses.; Muskegon River (Mich.); Ogemaw County (Mich.); Owosso (Mich.); Photographs.; Presque Ile County (Mich.)--Mills.; Roscommon County (Mich.); Shiawassee River (Mich.); Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Excavations (Archaeology)--Ontario.; Manitoulin Island (Ont.)
Genre Terms:
Field notes.
- Correspondence
  [Access to portions of these files is restricted; please contact the reference archivist for further information.]
  The Correspondence series, 1928-1965 (1.5 linear feet), contains Greenman's alphabetically arranged incoming and outgoing correspondence from his time at the Museum of Anthropology at the University of Michigan. Greenman's correspondence reflects his friendships with many Michigan amateur archaeologists, including Ira Butterfield, Fred Dustin, Wilbur Cunningham, Edmond P. Gibson and others. Some files include discussion of Michigan sites and initiatives, but a great deal of the correspondence relates to the business of the Michigan Archaeological Society; much of this correspondence is routine in nature, concerning memberships and publications. Access to portions of these files is restricted; please contact the reference archivist for further information.
  - A-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    [Restricted]
  - Baggerly, Carmen 1936-1958 (Box 1)
  - Beeson, Lewis 1955-1961 (Box 1)
  - Bender, Frank Jr. 1948-1950 (Box 1)
  - Benton, Robert 1938-1940 (Box 1)
  - Bloomfield, Leonard 1933-1937 (Box 1)
  - Burch, Homer L. 1951-1956 (Box 1)
  - Butterfield, Ira W. 1954-1962, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - B-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Cremation 1938 (Box 1)
  - Cunningham, Wilbur M. 1939-1957 (Box 1)
  - Cushman, Gwynne 1938-1959 (Box 1)
  - C-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Darling, Birt 1948-1957 (Box 1)
  - Davis, George W. 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - De Visscher, Jerry 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - Dever, Harry 1957-1961 (Box 1)
  - Dustin, Fred 1942-1957 (Box 1)
  - D-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Ellis, H. Holmes 1938-1960 (Box 1)
  - E-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Fox, George R. 1930-1957 (Box 1)
  - Franz, Harvey 1955-1962 (Box 1)
  - F-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Gagnon, E.J. 1948 (Box 1)
  - Gibson, Edmond P. 1951-1961, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Gillis, Edward V. 1955-1960 (Box 1)
  - Green, Amos R. 1938-1962 (Box 1)
  - Groesbeck, H.D. 1938-1940 (Box 1)
  - Guthe, Carl E. 1935-1940 (Box 1)
  - G-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Haltiner, Gerald 1951-1958 (Box 1)
  - Hampton, A.S. 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Hard, Robert 1954-1960 (Box 1)
  - Harvey, Wallace 1951-1963 (Box 1)
  - Hatt, Robert T. 1939-1961 (Box 1)
  - Herrick, Ruth 1952-1962 (Box 1)
  - Hill, Harry C. 1942 (Box 1)
  - Hoag, O.S. 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Hosack, Harry 1936-1949 (Box 1)
  - Hrdlicka, Ales 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Hyde, Edwin 1951-1954 (Box 1)
  - H-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - I-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Jenness, Diamond 1938-1942 (Box 1)
  - J-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Kempton, Rockwell M. 1942-1952 (Box 1)
  - Kinietz, Vernon 1938-1950 (Box 1)
  - Krogman, William M. 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - K-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Lambert, Margaret 1939-1958 (Box 1)
  - Lamorandiere, John 1949-1952 (Box 1)
  - Le Donne, Antoinette 1951-1954 (Box 1)
  - Lemmer, Victor F. 1954-1959 (Box 1)
  - L-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Mastin, Kathleen 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - McCoy, Raymond 1938-1940 (Box 1)
  - McCutcheon, Ted 1952 (Box 1)
  - McGregor, Gus 1938-1940 (Box 1)
  - McNairn, John S. 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - Messer, Donald and Lois 1951-1956 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Archaeological Society 1953-1958 (Box 1)
  - Mott, Harold 1953-1962 (Box 1)
  - M-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Needels, George 1938-1941 (Box 2)
  - Norton, Vaughn 1954-1958 (Box 2)
  - N-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - O-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Parchert, Karl G. 1952-1962 (Box 2)
  - Patterson, P.J. 1951-1954 (Box 2)
  - Pilling, Arnold 1958-1965 (Box 2)
    (includes photo)
  - Pomnitz, Charles E. 1954-1956 (Box 2)
  - Praus, Alexis 1949-1963 (Box 2)
  - P-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Quack, Douglas 1951-1958 (Box 2)
  - Quimby, George I. 1937-1952 (Box 2)
  - Ritchie, William A. 1937-1963 (Box 2)
  - R-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Schmidt, Walter 1938-1965 (Box 2)
  - Schneider, Robert 1936-1946 (Box 2)
  - Shetrone, H.C. 1936-1938 (Box 2)
  - Skinner, H. Alan 1955 (Box 2)
    (includes photos)
  - Spooner, Harry L. 1928-1939 (Box 2)
  - Stanley, George 1939-1949 (Box 2)
  - Stroebel, Ralph 1950-1964 (Box 2)
  - S-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - T-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - U-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Voegelin, Carl and Erminie 1936-1941 (Box 2)
  - V-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Weir, Alistair 1950-1956 (Box 2)
  - Wilmarth, Harold 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Wintemberg, W.J. 1937-1940 (Box 2)
  - Woodfill, W.S. 1943-1963 (Box 2)
  - W-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Y-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Z-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Unidentified (Box 2)
- Camp Killarney
  The Camp Killarney series, 1935-1955 (0.5 linear feet), contains materials related to the summer field school which Greenman led in Killarney in the Manitoulin District of the Ontario province of Canada from 1938 to 1953. From 1938 through 1946, the project was funded through Rackham Research Project R-10-A (originally established in 1935 as a more general research grant for "Michigan Indian History"); from 1946 through the program's official discontinuation in 1954, it was part of the university's Summer Session course schedule. Undergraduate and graduate students from the University of Michigan and other colleges and universities participated in field work and received course credit for Anthropology 255, Archaeological Field Methods. The series contains correspondence, reports, budget information, and supply lists related to the administration of the program (field notes, maps and journals can be found in the Canadian Site Files series). A very small amount of Greenman's personal correspondence received while he was in the field is also included in the files.
  - Accounting 1935-1944 (Box 2)
  - Administration
    - 1938-1945 (Box 2)
    - 1946-1948 (Box 2)
    - 1949-1951 (Box 2)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 2)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Archaeological Survey of the Silver Peak District 1948 (Box 2)
  - Course Materials 1940-1953 (Box 2)
- Research and Miscellaneous
  The Research and Miscellaneous series, 1924-1972 and undated (0.75 linear feet), consists of files related to Greenman's research, and personal and professional activities. The series includes several manuscripts by Greenman and others, information about Michigan archaeology, and a file related to the Great Lakes Research Institute. The most extensive set of files relates to Greenman's research into the connections between the Solutrean culture and the early cultures of the New World. Also included is a file of personal information related to Greenman's studies and employment at the university and a household ledger from Greenman's home at 2865 Gladstone Avenue in Ann Arbor.
  - Beothuk (Box 2)
  - Carlisle and Mount Pleasant Indian Schools 1934 (Box 2)
  - Glacial Geology (Box 2)
  - Great Lakes Research Institute 1944-1952 (Box 2)
  - Greenman
    - Household Ledger (Box 2)
    - Personal (Box 2)
    - Student Notes 1924-1926 (Box 3)
  - Indians and Michigan (Box 3)
  - Jim Pontiac 1933-1968 (Box 3)
    (claimed to be a grandson of Chief Pontiac)
  - Michigan Archaeological Society
    - Manuscripts (Box 3)
    - Microfilm Project 1956 (Box 3)
    - Sanilac Petroglyphs (Box 3)
  - Michigan Sites-Bay County, Macomb County, Saginaw and Wayne County 1937-1959 (Box 3)
  - Notes on Michigan Mounds and Native American Groups undated (Box 3)
  - Notes on Otchipwe Grammar undated (Box 3)
  - Single-Shouldered Points in Michigan (Box 3)
  - Solutrean
    - Caribbean and Couri 1965-1970 (Box 3)
    - Comments on "Le Solutreen" by Philip E.L. Smith undated (Box 3)
    - Early Man Culture (Box 3)
    - Military Hospital 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - Oceanographic Research 1965 (Box 3)
    - Research Trip to European Museums 1953-1955 (Box 3)
    - Resource Files, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Sandia 1955-1959 (Box 3)
    - Spain 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - "Terminology of the Palaeolithic," 1969 (Box 3)
    - Upper Paleolithic Painting (Box 3)
  - Washtenaw (meaning of word) 1972 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series, 1888-1958 (1 linear inch), consists of four envelopes of photographs. Subjects include log cabins and other nineteenth century houses and buildings, Owosso and Mackinac Island, Michigan, other Michigan views, and individual Native Americans. Most of the photographs were labeled by Greenman as to subject and date.
  - Log Cabins and Other Early Structures (Box 3)
  - Owosso, Mackinac Island (Box 3)
  - Michigan Views (Rivers, Lakes, etc.) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks, 13 volumes (Box 4)
  The Scrapbooks series, 1917-1959 (1 linear foot), is comprised of 13 scrapbooks of newspaper clippings about archaeology and Native Americans, mainly in Michigan and Ontario. The scrapbooks also include a number of clippings about Greenman and his professional activities. Some of the older scrapbooks appear to include contributions from W.B. Hinsdale.
- Canadian Site Files
  The Canadian Site Files series, 1930-1984 (2 linear feet), contains field notes, maps, journals, logs, correspondence, photographs, artifacts lists and other materials related to Greenman's field work in Ontario from the 1930s to 1950s. The series includes significant accumulations of documentation for a number of sites, including Killarney Bay (KB1), George Lake (GL1), Chikanising Creek (CH1) and Point Pelee. The series also includes field journals for work done in Manitoulin from 1939 to 1948. While most of the material relates to field work in which Greenman participated, the Point Pelee files relate to work done by others, mainly Stevens E. Sanderson. The Point Pelee files also include notes from Carl Guthe and an analysis of the Sanderson Collection of artifacts from 1984.
  - Artifacts List for CH1, GL1, KB1 (Box 5)
  - Ba1 1940 (Box 5)
  - Badgeley Island-Photographs (Box 5)
  - Canadian Sites-Correspondence 1938 (Box 5)
  - Chikanising Creek (CH1)
    - General, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Artifacts (Box 5)
    - Field Notes and Maps
      - 1939 (Box 5)
      - 1941 (Box 5)
      - 1946-1947 (Box 5)
      - 1948 (Box 5)
      - 1950-1952 (Box 5)
      - 1953 (Box 5)
    - Guide Maps (Box 5)
  - Collins Inlet (CI1)-Contour Map 1961 (Box 5)
  - Field Notes-MI1, MI2, LC1, WI1, LLC1 and West Bay Site 1938 (Box 5)
  - French River Site (FR1)-Field Notes
    - 1947 (Box 5)
    - 1950 (Box 5)
  - Geological Report-KB1, LC1, CH1 1939 (Box 5)
  - George Lake 1 (GL1)
    - Artifacts, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Field Notes
      - 1940-1941 (Box 5)
      - 1942 (Box 5)
      - 1945-1946 (Box 5)
    - Field Notes and Maps
      - 1947 (Box 5)
      - 1949-1950 (Box 5)
      - 1950-1952 (Box 5)
    - Index Information undated (Box 5)
    - Maps 1940s (Box 5)
    - Research 1949-1961 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1940-1953 (Box 5)
  - George Lake 2 (GL2)-Field Notes 1941 (Box 5)
  - Horton's Bluff 1951 (Box 5)
  - Killarney Bay (KB1)
    - General 1939-1941, undated (Box 5)
      (includes photographs and negatives)
    - Artifacts 1950-1951 (Box 5)
    - Drawings from Field 1941 (Box 5)
    - Field Notes and Maps
      - 1939 (Box 5)
      - 1940 (Box 5)
      - 1941 (Box 5)
      - 1942 (Box 5)
      - 1944 (Box 6)
      - 1946 (Box 6)
      - 1947 (Box 6)
      - 1948 (Box 6)
      - 1949-1950 (Box 6)
      - 1950 (Box 6)
      - 1951-1952 (Box 6)
      - 1953 (Box 6)
    - Lake-Levels and Succession of Cultures 1966 (Box 6)
    - Log 1940 (Box 6)
    - Map Lists 1939-1950 (Box 6)
  - Kreilich Site (STG5) (Box 6)
  - Manitoulin
    - Field Journal
      - 1939-1948 (in Box 7) (Box 6)
      - Summer 1938 (Box 6)
      - Summer 1939 (Box 6)
      - Summer 1940 (Box 6)
    - Site Locations (Box 6)
  - Manitowaning Bay-Photographs (Box 6)
  - Map and Photo Lists for GL1, KB1, MI8, MI9, and CH1 (Box 6)
  - McBean1 (McB1)-Field Notes and Maps 1952 (Box 6)
  - MI6, MI8, and MI9 1940 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Site Photos (Box 6)
  - Old Birch Island
    - Photographs (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Ontario-General Sites (Box 6)
  - Partridge Island-Field Notes 1939 (Box 6)
  - Point Pelee
    - General (Box 6)
    - Analysis of Sanderson Collection by Scarlett E. Janusas 1984 (Box 6)
    - Catalogue of Sanderson Material 1932 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence 1930-1932 (Box 6)
    - Expeditions Report 1930-1932 (Box 6)
    - Maps, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Notes from Carl Guthe on work by Steward and Hughes 1931 (Box 6)
    - Pottery Notes (Box 6)
    - Sanderson Collection (Box 6)
  - Port Clinton Mound 1932 (Box 6)
  - Providence Bay 1-Field Notes and Maps 1938 (Box 6)
  - Southwestern Ontario Survey 1949 (Box 6)
  - Tadoussac Site (Box 6)
  - Tyson Farm 1948 (Box 6)
  - Manitoulin
    - Field Journal
      - 1939-1948 (Box 7)